Guide to the Robert Provo Norris Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Watercolors and Drawings, Series IV
  - Watercolors: landscapes and architectural subjects, ca. 1846-51; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
    - Stone tower on coastline., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(7))
      Somewhat incomplete watercolor sketch of a rocky but flat coastline on which a tall stone tower (presumably a military lookout) appears. Blue mountains are seen on the waterfront in the background. Rocks are loosely sketched in the foreground. Unlabeled.
    - Cypress trees with man sitting under them, church tower in background., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 25 x 17.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(8))
      A fine watercolor showing a man in a blue jacket, beige pants, and pointed straw hat sitting on a stone block under a small grove of cypress trees. Beyond this area, which appears to be a fenced park, a stone tower rises in the center distance. Unlabeled.
    - Lookout tower or blockhouse on coastline/ Brushy rock chasm., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolors, one on each side of sheet; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(9))
      Watercolor sketch of a multi-storey stone lookout/blockhouse structure on flat coastline with rocky prominences. A ship is sketched loosely in the water and blue mountains lie on the distant shore.
      On the reverse side is an incomplete watercolor sketch of a brush-covered rocky chasm. The rock surfaces are reddish, with mountains seen in the distance.
      Neither image is labeled.
    - Stone fort buildings in grassy lowland, rocky feature on hilltop beyond., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(10))
      Watercolor image of stone buildings, likely part of a British fort. There is a large two-storey building and a smaller, lower, building to its side. A low wooden fence runs along a lush green space with trees and bushes--perhaps a garden or lawn area. The buildings lie in a grassy lowland, with a hill behind them. A rounded rocky formation rises at the hilltop in the background. Unlabeled.
    - Coastline fort / Wooden cabins., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolors, one on either side of sheet; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(11))
      Watercolor sketch of a mutli-storey stone fort sitting on a rocky coastline. The fort is seen at some distance, with the beach, a rocky formation, and the water in the foreground. Unlabeled.
      On the reverse is a watercolor and graphite sketch (incomplete) of wooden cabins. They appear to be part of some kind of settlement or military post. Trees are sketched in around the two cabins visible here. Unlabeled.
  - Watercolors: city views
    - Rooftop view of stone buildings with verandas, ships just off shore /Sketch of arched bridge., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolors, 1 on each side of sheet; 18 x 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5b(1))
      Watercolor sketch of a set of stone buildings with a low stone wall around them. The buildings have a couple of false fronts but are otherwise simple, with long pillared verandahs. Ships can be seen, their sails unfurled, in the body of water that lies just beyond this area. Mountains are ranged along the distant shoreline. Label is mostly illegible.
      On the reverse is an incomplete sepia wash sketch showing an arched bridge and a tall tree. Unlabeled.
    - View of stone buildings with verandas and false front / Mountainous chasm., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolors, one on either side of sheet; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5b(2))
      Watercolor sketch, incomplete, showing buildings with long pillared verandas seen in another of Norris's watercolors. The waterfront can be seen beyond these buildings. On the reverse side is a watercolor sketch of a craggy, grass and bush covered chasm or pass. Both images are unlabeled/unsigned.
  - Watercolors: people
    - "Eno: A Kaffir Chief.", circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor, tipped into decorative mat; 14.5 x 17 cm (Box 1, Folder 5c(1))
      Portrait of "Eno: A Kaffir Chief," showing a middle-aged African man with a leopard-skin cape draped around his shoulders. He wears a black beaded necklace and earring. His hair is cropped short. It is unclear how Norris came to paint this portrait--whether Eno was a prisoner of the British regiment or had some kind of pact of non-aggression with colonial forces.
      Xhosa (African people); Watercolors; Portraits
    - "Attack on Fort White, 3 January 1851.", 1851 January; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 15 x 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 5c(2))
      Watercolor sketch showing an encampment of Xhosa/"Kaffir" warriors in foreground, with the British Fort White seen in the middle-distance in a grassy valley floor. The warriors, who appear to be naked, hold rifles and are clustered in small groups here and there on a flat dusty area. There are no British troops seen in this image, done presumably sometime after the attack. Labeled in graphite on reverse. Unsigned.
      South Africa -- History -- Frontier Wars, 1811-1878; Watercolors; Xhosa (African people)
    - "Kaffirs" portrait of man, two women, and infant., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 26.5 x 18.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5c(3))
      Watercolor portrait of three Xhosa/"Kaffir" tribespeople. A man stands holding a long wooden implement, keeping his hands and body wrapped in a beige colored cloak. A woman with a beaded or colorful band around her breast, beige skirt, and golden bangles stands holding a small wooden or woven bowl. Another woman kneels in the foreground holding a bushel of reeds. She has an infant strapped to her back. It is not known whether the three subjects posed for this portrait or were observed from a distance by Norris. Labeled in graphite. Unsigned.
    - Xhosa /"Kaffir" man addressing tribe members., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 18.5 x 26.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5c(4))
      Watercolor sketch of a Xhosa/"Kaffir" man standing to address other assembled tribespeople. The standing man wears a leopard cloak draped over one shoulder, an arm- and waist-band of thin woven or metal material, and has a necklace. His body is largely uncovered, while the gathered men are mostly wrapped up in beige capes. They look attentively at him as he speaks, pointing his finger towards some object in the distance at right. They are gathered in a dusty stretch of lowland. Colors are labeled on reverse in pen and ink and graphite title reads, "Fancy [?] sketch of Kaffirs." Unsigned/undated.
      Watercolors; Xhosa (African people)
    - "Meeting of Kaffirs on 21 Dec[ember] 1850 at Fort Cox...to Meet Sir H. Smith.", 1850 December; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor with graphite sketch on reverse; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5c(5))
      Watercolor depicts assembly of Xhosa/"Kaffir" people outside the Fort Cox buildings. Inside, presumably, is Sir Harry Smith, the colonial governor, who held a meeting with Xhosa leaders in late December, 1850. The watercolor is loose in style, with people depicted as vertical dashes of brown paint with darker brown dots for heads. The sketch is labeled in graphite. This meeting was to be the last of its kind before war again broke out within days.
      On the reverse is a loose graphite sketch of a wooded area with low squarish buildings at left. It is labeled "Mick [?]."
      South Africa -- History -- Frontier Wars, 1811-1878; Xhosa (African people); Watercolors
    - "Cape Corps," portrait of an African man in military garb., 1850 November; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 21.5 x 17.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5c(6))
      Watercolor portrait, full-length, of an African man with a moustache wearing a British or European military costume. He has a billed cap (with initials "C.M.R." for "Cape Mounted Rifles" embroidered or stamped on it) and a tight, high-collared, jacket, both in dark blue, and beige trousers. He also wears black leather boots. He stands with arms crossed, looking sideways at the viewer. A metal sword is slung at his waist. In graphite are sketched mounted military men, at considerable distance in the background. The image is labeled in graphite.
  - Graphite drawings: people
    - Mounted officer riding a galloping horse., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 graphite sketch; 18.5 x 22.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(1))
      A detailed graphite drawing of an officer in full uniform (including cape, tall hat, and sash) astride a horse who runs or leaps with wide eyes and outstretched feet. The officer looks back over his shoulder and his sword is held out in his right hand. His heavy saddle and other equipment are shown clearly. Unlabeled.
      Graphite drawings; Horses in art
    - Jockey on horseback with dog., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 graphite sketch; 16.5 x 20.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(2))
      Graphite sketch of a jockey or rider in a lightweight cap and riding clothes astride a horse who leaps or gallops forward. A dog is shown running alongside the horse, although the dog has been sketched over with shading/cross-hatching. The image is initialed "RN." It likely represents a scene from one of the many horse races that Norris seemed fond of attending while in the Cape Town area.
      Graphite drawings; Horse racing
    - African (Xhosa?) woman carrying baskets on her head., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 graphite sketch; 18.5 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(3))
      An African woman is seen from behind in this apparently incomplete sketch. She bears three baskets on her head and carries a fourth basket in her hand. She wears some kind of band-like top, with a wrapped long skirt. Her feet are bare and she wears bracelets on her wrists. A palm tree is sketched loosely at left. Unlabeled.
      Graphite drawings; Portraits; Xhosa (African people)
    - Portrait of a young man., 1836; 1 graphite sketch; 18.5 x 13.8 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(4))
      Graphite portrait by an accomplished artist, showing a young man who appears to be in his twenties. The subject has large clear eyes, long sideburns, and no beard. He has a pleasant expression and wears a high-collared jacket, shirt, and cravat. It is unlikely that the subject is Robert Provo Norris, as the drawing is initialed and dated, " ER. 1836," and Robert would have been only ten years old at the time. The portraitist, "ER," is unidentified.
      On the reverse is a partial and incomplete graphite portrait of another sitter.
      Portraits; Graphite drawings
  - Graphite drawings: landscapes
    - "Panoramic" view of military buildings and encampment., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 graphite sketch; 23 x 50 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(5))
      The sketch is unsigned and unidentified, although it has "Road" written faintly to indicate a narrow road running in the foreground. An unusual building with two stories and a hinged sort of structure atop it is seen here. A sentry stands on guard near a small post. Another building is visible at left and there are trees and a small tent. The image carries over past the folded edge and onto the reverse. A military encampment is sketched faintly on the last two portions.
      Graphite drawings
    - View of a lowland or valley floor with hills in distance/ "Fort White.", circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 graphite sketches, one on either side of sheet; 17.5. x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(6))
      Graphite sketch of a British fort in a low-lying grassy area. Hills can be seen in distance. Labeled, "Fort White."
      On the reverse is a graphite sketch of a grassy lowland with hills in distance. It appears to depict a location similar to that shown on the opposite side of the sheet, so it is likely of the area surrounding Fort White.
    - Tents inside a fort/Incomplete sketch of tents., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 graphite sketches, one on either side of sheet; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(7))
      Graphite sketch of tents set up on the inside yard of a stone fort. There are seventeen tents, all assembled at close quarters to one another. Presumably, these were officers' tents, much like the one Robert Provo Norris occupied (according to his diary). This is a detailed depiction. Unlabeled.
      On the reverse is a view at slightly closer range of the same tents. Though incomplete, this image shows one tent's structure and rigging in some greater detail. Unlabeled.
    - Coastline with mountains and ships in water., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 graphite sketch; 16.5 x 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(8))
      Graphite sketch, somewhat incomplete, of tall brushy mountains, whose tops are obscured by clouds, towering over a coastal settlement. A few ships can be seen in the water. Unlabeled.
  - Pen and ink drawings
    - Sketch of an officer in uniform., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 pen and ink sketch, with a partial (torn off) watercolor on the reverse; 17.5 x 12.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5d(9))
      Pen and ink sketch of an officer wearing a feathered and visored helmet and full uniform. He stands with his sword pointed at the ground. A loose profile is sketched above this image.
      On the reverse is part of a watercolor landscape, torn in half. Graphite scribblings and writing covers this watercolor, with some handwriting practiced and the name "Carles Henry de Rouvignes" written at the bottom of the page. It is unclear why this name appears here, although similar scribblings appear over another of the pieces in this collection.
      Portraits; Pen and ink drawings
  - Watercolors: landscapes and exterior/natural settings
    - Rocky coastline scene /unfinished shoreline village., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolor and graphite sketches, 1 on reverse side of the other; 25 x 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(1))
      Watercolor sketch showing a rocky coastline with large mountains stretching up from water at left, a small building on the shore towards the foreground at left, and a curving dirt road or path in the immediate foreground. Unsigned/unidentified.
      On the reverse: an incomplete watercolor and graphite sketch of a shoreline village. Natural features are painted with a light wash of color and buildings and other features remain only outlined in graphite.
    - Unfinished tree with rocky shore in the distance., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 25 x 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(2))
      Unfinished watercolor sketch showing a grassy area in foreground with a tree at left. Purplish rocky hills rise along a coastline seen in the background. Unsigned and unidentified.
    - "Near [?] Zanderend," river and mountains / "River Loudes [East London?] End" graphite sketch., circa 1846-1851; 1 watercolor with a graphite sketch (incomplete) on reverse; 17.5 x 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(3))
      Watercolor scene of a calm river with spiky green plants growing at banks in foreground and at left. On the left shoreline are bulbous rocks and trees. Lowlands extend to the right, and large mountains rise in the distance. The watercolor is signed, "Near [?] Zanderend," suggesting it was done near the Zander End mountain range/river.
      On the reverse is a loose graphite sketch of a five-pillared bridge. It is labeled "River Loudes [?] End," but possibly indicates the area of East London, a South African port city.
    - Zander End scene /graphite sketch of coastal buildings., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor, with graphite sketch on reverse; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(4))
      Watercolor image of the Zander End river/mountains. A similar image to another in Norris's watercolors. This version appears to be slightly more complete, with a more finished look to details. The watercolor is done with careful attention to detail. Unlabeled.
      On the reverse is an incomplete graphite sketch of some low tower-like lookouts on a rocky bit of coastline, along with other stone buildings. The sketch is partial, and other graphite 'doodles' suggest that the paper was used to practice drawing shapes (a horse's head and architectural features are loosely sketched here). Unlabeled.
    - Village in grassy hills /"Fort Cox," distant view., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolors, one on either side of sheet; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(5))
      Watercolor scene of grassy hills dotted with brush and trees. Low stone buildings, presumably part of Fort Cox, are seen on a hilltop in the background. Unlabeled.
      On the reverse is an image of two African men sitting in the foreground, one of whom looks towards Fort Cox, which can be seen as a congregation of many buildings and tents grouped on neighboring hilltops. A dirt road connects the various parts of the fort and its outlying buildings. Labeled in graphite.
    - Brushy hills and mountains / Zander End view., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolors, one on either side of sheet; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(6))
      Watercolor view of brushy, grassy, hills and purplish mountains in distance. A few buildings appear at the right.
      On the reverse is an image of the Zander End river/mountains that feature a few times in Norris's paintings. Neither image is complete. Unsigned/unlabeled.
    - "__amber's _op, Taben-Dodo, June 51, In front of Fort White" hilltop beyond a dusty lowland., 1851 June; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(7))
      Watercolor sketch of a dusty lowland in foreground with brushy hill rising to a slightly rocky peak in the background. A dirt path appears to wind up towards the peak. The title is not completely legible, but indicates that this image is of a location in the Tabendodo Mountains (a name which seems to have become obsolete).
    - "Cape Town/Henry de ____[?]", circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor and 1 watercolor-and-graphite sketch, on either side of sheet; 10 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5e(8))
      Small watercolor sketch of Cape Town, done with fine attention to detail. Scene shows two people standing at some distance from foreground, under a group of cypress trees. They look down through hills on either side to the town at the base, on the shore. Mountains are shown on the distant coast. Labeled in graphite.
      On reverse is a rough graphite/sepia wash sketch of an African man wearing a pointed straw sunhat. Written in graphite is the name, "Henry de ___," along with other graphite scribblings, done as though to practice handwriting.